<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from an officer in His Majesties army, to a gentleman in Glocester-shire. Upon occasion of certain querees scattered about that country.</title>
            <author>Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1724</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E101_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18322</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860388</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860388</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155896</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155896)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E101[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from an officer in His Majesties army, to a gentleman in Glocester-shire. Upon occasion of certain querees scattered about that country.</title>
                  <author>Heylyn, Peter, 1600-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by L. Lichfield],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: 10th of April, 1643.</note>
                  <note>The queries concern the continuing of Parliament, the Kings protection of delinquents, and the papists.</note>
                  <note>By Peter Heylyn -- Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Publisher and place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oxford in may".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155896:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> LETTER FROM AN OFFICER in His MAJESTIES Army, to a Gentleman in <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>UPON OCCASION OF certain Querees ſcattered about <hi>that Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:155896:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155896:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> LETTER FROM AN OFFICER IN HIS MAJESTIES ARMY, to a Gentleman in <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire.</hi> Upon occaſion of certain Quaerees ſcattered about that COUNTRY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have received your Letter and your Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rees, which you ſay makes a deep impreſſion in many of whoſe honeſty and publique Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections I have a very good eſteem, and that they are made by one who hath a great deſire to receive caſe and ſatisfaction himſelfe, as being of a nature very undelighted and paſſive in theſe diſtractions. The firſt (how ſtrange ſoever it ſeems to Reaſon) I muſt beleive, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when I find your ſelfe, whom I have often known very eaſily to maſter more difficult Contentions, brought to ſome pauſe, as it ſomewhat were ſaid to you, you could not well get from; no doubt many other of leſſe ſubtle underſtandings, and it may be hurt by the neceſſary preſſures, and provoked by unwarrantable Inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Kings Souldiers, are, or ſeem to be really puzled. But for the Author of thoſe Quaerees, you muſt pardon me if I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive him to be a man of ſo innocent a nature as you would imply: doubtleſſe theſe ſcruples never ſprung from a minde in labour to find out truth; but are contrived by a Perſon very well able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his own Objections, and having pretended Conſcience againſt his own underſtanding hath found theſe little excuſes to make a party amongſt weaker men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155896:3"/>
The firſt Scruple ſeems to be a tenderneſſe of the Act for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Parliament, which that Gentleman would apprehend to be broken by His <hi>Majeſties</hi> not conſenting to all the Counſells now given Him by both Houſes; If I thought this Objection to be of moment to you, I ſhould give your underſtanding for loſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect your cure only by that which miſled you, Succeſſe; but I muſt obſerve to you the uningenuity of your honeſt man, who would make the People beleive that by His <hi>Majeſties</hi> conſenting to paſſe that Act, that Aſſembly were authorized to command, and His <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> obliged to obey whatever they preſcribed; when that Gentleman well knowes nothing is enacted by that law, but that this Parliament ſhall not be diſſolved but by Act of Parliament. You well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in what Condition things ſtood at the paſſing that Law, two Armies in the Bowells of the Kingdome at 800001. the Moneth, ſo much to be raiſed for the ſupport of them, and a much greater ſumme to Disband them; all this Money was to be borrowed, and upon ſuch ſecurity as Money in thoſe happy daies uſed to be lent, for the new merry ſecurity of the publique faity, by a Vote of both Houſes, was not then currant enough to be obtruded to the people, the Credit of many worthy Perſons was to be uſed for the procuring this ſupply, and it ſeemed no unſeaſonable warineſſe of thoſe who expoſed themſelves and their fortunes to this hazard; to deſire that the body, at whoſe inſtance they undertook thoſe Engagements, might not be diſſolved, before it had taken ſome courſe to ſecure ſuch undertakings, and proviſion ſhould be made for the indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of thoſe who had ſubmitted to ſuch burthens. This Reaſon, and this alone prevailed with His <hi>Majeſty</hi> to agree that this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould not be diſſolved without their conſent, who ſeemed vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily to engage themſelves for the Peace &amp; benefit of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. How this continuance of the Parliament ſhould now give both Houſes the Prerogative they have aſſumed, I cannot underſtand, and themſelves have publiquely acknowledged in their Declarations, that they were to blame if they undertook any thing which they would not undertake, if it were in His <hi>Maieſties</hi> power to diſſolve them to morrow; Think now with your ſelfe if the King ſhould ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with both Houſes upon their own Grounds, that the Truſt being broken, the power may be reaſſumed immediately into the hands which repoſed that Truſt, might he not juſtly ſay, that they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155896:3"/>
and forfeited that Truſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by uſing the meanes which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to disburthen the Common-wealth of a debt which was then thought inſupportable, only to plunge it irrecoverably into a greater, and to ruine the Kingdom to preferre halfe a ſcore men. And if the People ſhould follow their Logique and be tryed only by the Equity of the Law, might they not charge them with the breach of Truſt, in changing the whole frame of the Government of the Kingdom, and ſubjecting them to ſo unlimited an Arbitrary power, that no man can know at the ſitting of the Houſes, what he ſhall be worth at their riſing? Did they intend, when they let theſe men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Aſſembly, that they ſhould ſhut the Door, and keep thoſe that ſent them for ever from thoſe Counſells? Did the King intend that they ſhould rob, depoſe &amp; murther him? And did the people intend that their fellowes and Companions ſhould impriſon, plunder and deſtroy them? and if the abuſed King, and injured people ſhould now declare this Act to be void and in it ſelfe againſt the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes of the Kingdom, and ſo this Parliament to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, would not your Principles and foundations beare them out? You are one of the oldeſt Parliament men I know, and, however you may have ſince changed your mind, have to me ſeemed the moſt ſcandalized at the Indignities offered to the very being of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the wildneſſe and fury of this. Did not you paſſionately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the pert Burgeſſe of your own Town, for arguing againſt the Kings negative voyce, becauſe then it may fall out that the Common-wealth might be ruined for want of a ſupplementall Law, which the perverſeneſſe of one man would not conſent to? Did you not then, after you had ſhewed the impoſſibility and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſuch ſuppoſitions, and that from the beginning of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy to this day, no inconvenience had hapned of that kind, ſay, that you were perſwaded in your Conſcience, that the Lawes of the Kingdome were ſo very compleat, in order to the Government of the Kingdome, that if there ſhould never more be made, ſo the old were faithfully obſerved, the Kingdome would be at leaſt without any diminution of its happineſſe: on the other ſide if the Kings Conſent were not neceſſary, you ſaid all thoſe Bills which had here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore paſſed both Houſes, and for want of the Royall Aſſent had been layed by, would now riſe vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo many Lawes to as great a confuſion as theſe Ordinances have made? Did you not then ſay,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155896:4"/>
that when <hi>Parliaments</hi> left their modeſty, they would looſe their Reputation, and when they walked in any other Path then of their knowne Preſidents, and judged by any other Rule then the known Lawes, they would advance a Tyranny more inſupportable then ever <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Greece</hi> endured? your Priviledges, which are free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Speech, and freedome from Impriſonment, (except where the Law ſayes you may be impriſoned) where are they? how vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated? and by whom, but by your ſelves? How many men, choſen &amp; ſent by their Countries, have you turned out of the Houſe for not concurring with you in opinion? How monſtrous is it that the King may not commit a Member, who attempts to kill Him, without your leave; &amp; you may commit another for but deſiring to kiſſe His hand? And whileſt you will not ſuffer His Majeſty, without breach of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, to commit Traitors and Felons, becauſe they are Members of either Houſe, you are content that Alderman <hi>Pennington,</hi> or any of the City Captaines commit thoſe who ſit amongſt you, &amp; you have not the courage to reprehend them. Doe you thinke the people of <hi>England</hi> can look long upon ſixſcore or ſevenſcore men (for both Houſes doe not containe a greater number) as upon the high Court of <hi>Parliament?</hi> when the Major part of thoſe too are Perſons of ſuch deſperate fortunes, and contemptible underſtandings, as off from thoſe Benches were never thought fit for ſober and honeſt Counſells. You may break what leſts you pleaſe upon the King and the Cavaliers, &amp; ſay, that if He were in His owne Power He would quickly returne to His <hi>Parliament,</hi> but truly the Court here hath ſo much Charity to beleeve, if both Houſes were at liberty to doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Conſciences this publique fire would be quickly quenched. Beleeve it no ſober man lookes upon you under any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Notion, then as men beſieged by the deſperate common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of <hi>London</hi> and their Adherents, who awe and fright you to their wicked and damnable concluſions<hi>:</hi> Nay, the cloſe Committee it ſelf, is a greater breach of the Priviledge of <hi>Parliament,</hi> then the Kings comming to the Houſe, &amp; the taking the five Members from thence could have been. I am as little pleaſed with the perpetuity of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> as I have been with the untimely breaking of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and let me tell you, all the diſſolutions of <hi>Parliaments</hi> from the beginning of them to this time, hath not done halfe that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, as the continuance of this hath done; and yet ſince it hath the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155896:4"/>
countenance of a Law, I wiſh it may never be diſſolved but by a Law. What deſignes theſe men have even upon Parliaments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, is too evident, whereas if the King prevailes, parliaments are againe reſtored to their full Luſtre; you have read His Proteſtations ſolemnly made in the preſence of God for the defence of the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of <hi>Parliaments;</hi> He is too Iuſt and too pious a Prince to break thoſe promiſes, and to reproach Himſelfe with His owne Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but if He ſhould, enquire whether the Perſons about Him, even the Officers of His Army are likely to concur with Him in thoſe ends? I am perſwaded it would be no more in His Power to employ His Army to the deſtruction of the Law, then you once thought it was to raiſe one for His preſervation. In a word, as you eſteem and reverence reall <hi>Parliaments,</hi> abhorre theſe men who would uſe the word <hi>Parliament</hi> only as a ſtalking Horſe to deſtroy all acts of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> there cannot be a more irreverent mention of <hi>Parliaments</hi> then to call the fanatique actions of a few deſperate ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the proceedings of <hi>Parliament.</hi> A <hi>Parliament</hi> is the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Kingdome, gratiouſly called by His <hi>Maieſiies</hi> Writ, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently to preſent the grievances of the people, and humbly to offer their advice and Counſells for Reformation; if they come unſent for, irregularly call that a greivance, which the Law allowes, and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently command, inſtead of modeſtly adviſing the Royall power, by whoſe Authority they come together, they doe, as much as in them lyes, diſſolve the <hi>Parliament</hi> by proceeding againſt the nature, of <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next ſcandall this wiſe Gentleman takes, is at the protecting Delinquents; does this trouble you too? Call your memory to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I think I have heard you ſay, you have been of eight <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> How many Delinquents have you known ſent for in ſeven of them? and what were they? were not moſt of them, only ſuch as had preſumed to ſue or arreſt priviledged perſons? How many men in your time have you knowne committed by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons before this <hi>Parliament?</hi> doe you think it reaſonable that they who cannot examine, ſhould have power to Iudge? you had need take the courſe you doe to ſlight and undervalue all Oaths, that they may not be thought neceſſary to legall and regular proceedings, and yet why doe you then at all intimate your owne incompetency by ſome times deſiring the Lords to helpe you examine men by Oath?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155896:5"/>
How comes it that you confeſſe Oathes at ſome time to be neceſſary for finding out the truth, and paſſe it over as impertinent at other? When you have evidence you think it a popular thing to uſe it, if you have none, you can Iudge as well without it. You have a trick to be ſatisfied in your owne Conſciences, (Conſciences that can commit Treaſon, Felony, Rapes, and Sacriledge in the feare of God) &amp; then all formes and eſſences of proceedings, which can only diſtinguiſh right from wrong, muſt be diſpenſed with. If a Treaſon were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, how comes my Lord Chief Iuſtice to be left out in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, and no other Miniſter imployed but your Sergeant? why ſhould not the Common-wealth heare of Treaſon and Miſpriſion of Treaſon in <hi>Weſtminster</hi> Hall, where the termes are underſtood, but only in the Houſe of Commons? If a man ſhould come to the Houſe of Commons-Barre, and deſire the Sergeant of that Houſe ſhould be ſent for a man as Delinquent, who took his Purſe from him upon <hi>Black-Heath,</hi> or picked his pocket in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> if the Theif were not a Member of either Houſe (God forbid but they ſhould have the Priviledge to Iudge one another) would you not thinke the fellow mad, &amp; wiſh him to goe to the next Miniſter of Iuſtice? How come you to be ſo ſubtile to be able only to Iudge and define Treaſons; about which your Anceſtors have been ſo carefull, to leave it in the view of any man what it is? Tell your ſelfe without bluſhing, who you thinke are meant by Delinquents<hi>:</hi> Is it not viſible to all the world, that you intend all ſuch who are not or will not be Traitors to the knowne Lawes, to be Delinquents to both Houſes? and 'tis a notable breach of Priviledge that His Majeſty will protect theſe Delinquents from you; look over your own votes, and ſee if all men who doe not aſſiſt you in your pious worke of murthering the King, and deſtroying the Common-wealth, (for you have faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the lazy Gentlemen who deſired to be lookers on) are not comprehended in the number of Delinquents: What was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> for denying His Majeſty admittance into His owne Towne of <hi>Hull?</hi> A priviledged Perſon and an upright Patriot, what were they who attended His Majeſty when He preſumed deſperately and rebelliouſly to offer to goe thither? Delinquents: And yet His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will not ſuffer thoſe who kept Him out, to Iudge thoſe who would have gone in with Him; wonderfull breach of priviledge, and protecting of Delinquents! If we cannot recover Law againe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155896:5"/>
for Gods ſake let us have ſenſe reſtored to us, and not grow Beaſts in our underſtanding as well as in our Liberty; it will make us love mankind the worſe to ſee men with ſad browes, as if they believed themſelves, ſeriouſly urge things in publique, which in private would make friends quarrell for the ſcorne and Indignity offered to reaſon, ſuch is all your diſcourſe of Priviledges and Delinquents.</p>
            <p>But you have at laſt found a pretty obligation upon your ſelves to Rebell againſt Law and Reaſon, your late Proteſtation requires all this at your hands, in the behalfe of the Priviledges of Parliament, which by that you are bound to defend, and ſo you reſcue your ſelves from the duty of Allegiance, to which you have regularly and legally ſworn, by a voluntary Proteſtation to doe ſomewhat you doe not underſtand; If there be any thing by that Proteſtation en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to be done, which was unlawfull to be done before the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation was taken, 'tis no more to be juſtified by that Act, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other unlawfull thing is by a raſh and wicked Vow, entred into by a Perſon who deſires to doe miſchiefe; If there be nothing in it, but what before was the duty of every man, there needs no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Proteſtation; The truth is, though I like not the uſe hath been made of it to poyſon and miſlead ſimple people, nor the irregularity (to call it no worſe) of compelling men to take it, when no Law requires it, I know nothing promiſed or undertaken in that Proteſtation which every honeſt man doth not, and alwaies did hold abſolutely to be his duty, no man being obliged by it to doe any thing, but as farre as Lawfully he may. And would not a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by think a man mad, that ſhould ſwear to defend the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to maintain the Priviledges of Parliament, and immediatly draw His ſword upon the King whoſe Perſon he knew, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of ſomewhat he is told is Priviledge of Parliament? we are gotten again into the old circle of folly and madneſſe.</p>
            <p>Your laſt Scruple I will be ſerious with you in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'tis that (howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thrown among the people malitiouſly, and indeed againſt the Conſcience of the Contrivers) which I know ſtartles many well meaning, and well wiſhing men, you are afraid of the Papiſts, and that if the King prevailes, that Religion will have too great a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and growth, to the ſcandall of ours; Indeed if this fear were well grounded, you would have ſo many partners with you in your trouble, that you would even be ſatisfied in your company,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155896:6"/>
and by that, think your ſelfe ſecure againſt your fears; what makes you doubt this, an Inclination in the King Himſelfe? Let His life be examined, His continued publique Acts of Devotion, (exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples indeed for a through Reformation) His underſtanding the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and us, and ſo not only utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſenting from them, but knowing why he doth ſo, and He will be found above the reach of Envy or Malice, and indeed above your own feares and jealouſies<hi>:</hi> Take a liſt and ſurvey of His Servants and Counſellors, who are ſuſpected to have the leaſt intereſt in His fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and inclinations, you will not find a man under the leaſt taint that way, and moſt of them (till your diſhoneſt uncharitable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Popiſh and Popiſhly affected was thrown among the people) thought eminent advancers of the true Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed. And let me tell you, if there ſhould be a breach made upon that Religion, theſe men would ſtand in the Gap, when halfe your Zelots would ſubmit to an Alteration, if it brought any ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to their worldly Ambition. But you ſay the Queene is of that Religion, and Shee hath a great influence and power over His affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and you think it an unkingly thing to be a good Husband, and whileſt your ſelves are guided and ſwayed by other mens Wives (for 'tis not Women you are angry with, you allow them whole ſharers with you in your miſchiefes) you cannot endure He ſhould ſo much as adviſe with His own; indeed I cannot blame you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to keep Him from any Converſation with one you have uſed ſo ill<hi>:</hi> But how comes this Melancholy upon you now, Is Shee more a Catholique now then She was fifteen years ſince? Why did not theſe Fears and Iealouſies break out into Rebellion when He was firſt Married? before the Nation knew any thing of Her, but Her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? After the experience of ſo many yeares; after the enriching the Kingdom with ſo hopefull and numerous an Iſſue, after the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging all ſorts of People with Her favours, without diſobliging any body that I have heard of, after fifteen years living here with great expreſſions of Love and Affection to the Engliſh Nation, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other activity in Religion, then to live well, and wiſh well to Her owne, with equall eſteem of thoſe who are not of the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to deſire to break and interrupt that excellent Harmony in Affections, is an ingratitude, an impiety worthy the contrivers of theſe bloody diſtempers<hi>:</hi> Look into the Perſons who have received
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155896:6"/>
the greateſt teſtimonies &amp; evidence of Her favours, you will not find them to be Popiſh or Popiſhly affected, but in the liſt of your own Religious Men and Godly Women; If you will convert Her, let your Charity and Humility, the principles of true Religion, let your Obedience and Loyalty, the effects of true Religion, be an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to Her that yours is the right; the courſe you take will rather fright good People from any, then invite them to yours; She is a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy too well underſtands Her own ſhare, and Her own adventure in the publique diſtractions, not to endeavour with Her ſoule a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation of them, I would your Ladies were like Her, She is as farre from revenge of Injuries and Indignities, as from deſerving them. You have the advantage in your Provocations, you have met with tempers as apt to forgive, as you are to offend, who are as unlimited in their mercy as their enemies are in their inſolencies, make good uſe of it, ſet your hearts upon Peace, and you will eaſily find the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> way to it, be once ingenious, and you will be quickly ſafe.</p>
            <p>But oh the great Army of Papiſts, if that were disbanded, your feares and jealouſies would infinitely abate; that's well; pray ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how theſe Papiſts come together<hi>:</hi> Remember <hi>Nottingham</hi> when you had a formed Army of 10000. men and His Majeſty not 800. Muſkets at His command in all His dominions? if you had then fallen upon Him and deſtroyed Him, as, if Your Pride had not been greater then your Loyalty, you had done; you meant to ſtrip Him by Votes and Ordinances of all Succors and Aſſiſtance, that He ſhould be compelled to put Himſelfe into your hands for Protection, and ſo confeſſe your Army to be raiſed for His defence. Would not now all Chriſtian Princes have thought His Majeſty guilty of His own undoing, who would not ſuffer Himſelfe to receive Aid from any of His own Subjects, though they were Papiſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You tell me the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of theſe Queries is learned in the Lawes; pray get him to ſhew you one Law, whereby the Papiſts are inhibited to ſerve their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne againſt a Rebellion, becauſe Papiſts may not come neer the Court without the Kings leave, or weare Armes, may not a Papiſt ride poſt to tell the King of a deſigne to murther Him? or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent take away a ſword from that man who attempts to kill Him? Sure there is no Law hath prohibited the Allegiance of the Papiſts, and becauſe they will not come to Church, forbid them to be Subjects. If a Fleet arrived from France or Spaine to invade us
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155896:7"/>
were it not law full for a Papiſt to endeavour to deſtroy that Fleet? and muſt he ſit ſtill in a Rebellion, and ſee his Soveraigne, and the Lawes of the Land (in which he hath an equall intereſt with any other Subject) in imminent, viſible danger to be deſtroyed, and muſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> either? yet obſerve now (how much ſoever you ſeem to be ſcandalized at it) what you your ſelves have done towards the raiſing this Army of Papiſts, and indeed if there be ſuch an Army, whether your ſelves have not raiſed it, without breaking your own Ieſts and ſaying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is myſed by the power of both Houſes, as yours is by the Kings Authority you ſeize upon all the papiſts eſtates, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Houſes, impriſon their perſons, without the leaſt Colour of Law, leaving them no place to breath in but under the ſhelter of the Kings Army, and thence you would have the King drive them too, for being papiſts. You ſuffer Mr. <hi>Griffith</hi> to raiſe a Troop of that Religion for your ſervice and when they caſhiere their Captain, and come in to His Majeſty, you would have Him disband them becauſe they are Papiſts. For Gods ſake get one of your Orators to make a Speech for the King to a papiſt, who ſhall ſay to him; Sir, I have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved modeſtly and dutifully at my own Houſe, without aſſuming to my ſelfe any Licence which the Law gave me not, I have humbly ſubmitted to the penalties impoſed on me, and contented my ſelfe with what the Law hath left mee, I am driven from thence by force of Armes, my Eſtate taken from mee, my liberty endeavoured to be ſo too, I am Your Subject, and You are my King, vouchſafe me the Protection You owe mee. what anſwer ſhall He make; Sir, you are a Papiſt, and you ſhall not come neere Mee, or, Sir, I am content you ſhall be under the ſhelter and ſecurity of my Forces, but upon your life uſe no weapon, beare no Armes, help them not though they are in danger to be cut in pieces before your face. Let a ſober man find a way to get out here, to be a King and not protect them. And after all this what a goodly Army of Papiſts hath His Majeſty got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not to compare with you, for you ſay 'tis no matter what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Papiſts you have, becauſe there are no Feares and Iealouſies of your favouring of popery; I am confident and I have my Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from no ill hands, that in all His Majeſties <hi>Armies</hi> the Papiſts cannot make one good Regiment. Get but the honeſt ſober, true Proteſtants once of your mind, and my life upon it, you ſhall not ſee the papiſts grow above the Reach of the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:155896:7"/>
Here is an end of your Author, a word now to your own Letter, I find you much tranſported with the apprehenſion of Gods won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Bleſſings upon the proceedings of both Houſes, that their progreſſe and Succeſſe hither to hath not been leſſe then miraculous; Indeed there are negative Miracles, as well as affirmative, for God to forbeare what according to his Iuſtice and goodneſſe, and other attributes We might expect from him by the way of puniſhment &amp; revenge, is a miracle of his mercy, in this Senſe, the world which hath ſeen your Treaſon and Rebellion, your Acts of Injuſtice, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Inhumanity, your Lying and Blaſphemy, your Prophaneſſe and Sacriledge (if your Divines have left you the apprehenſion of ſuch a Sinne (and by the way if they have, pray ſend me word what they meane by it) they who have obſerved the ill Arts you have uſed to compaſſe things in themſelves lawfull, and the wicked Arts you dayly uſe to compaſſe things unlawfull, and ſee that ſtones in the Streets have not riſen up againſt you, and fire from Heaven hath not conſumed you, muſt ſay you have tempted God ſo farre, ſo inſolently, that leſſe then a Miracle could not preſerve you. Bate me this one Miracle, &amp; tell me if the hand of God hath not been upon you and purſued you from the firſt houre you entred into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, are you not fallen from your univerſall Intereſt &amp; Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the people, to that degree of hatred that they curſe you to your face? Are you not ſhrunke from the honour and Reverence due to a <hi>Parliament</hi> to the Imputation of a vile crowd of mean, guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſeditious perſons? Doe nor your friends every day forſake you, and thoſe perſons of Quality whom'you miſlead, with more bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe fall from you, then your firſt Delinquents? Are not your own Weapons turned upon you, and are you not afraid of thoſe Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whom with ſo much skill and Induſtry you taught to Petition? Is not your owne Army, raiſed and maintained by your ſelves, grown ſo undevoted to you, that ſome Commanders every day leave you, and others are committed by you for feare they will doe ſo too? Are you not brought to that ſtrait as to feare a Mutiny for want of Pay, and not to dare to pay for feare of a disbanding? Have you not by blood and Rapine, with the curſes of all good men gotten the Treaſure of the Kingdome into your hands, and waſted it ſo, that your wants are as not orious as your Crimes? Laſtly, are you not ſo jealous, ſo divided amongſt your ſelves, that if your Army pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155896:8"/>
to morrow, you were as farre from compaſſing your owne ends, as when you began your deſperate undertaking, your principall Commanders being as farre from their ends, who couzened them into this Rebellion, as the prime Cavaliers in the Kings Army, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting only their Affection to the Kings Perſon.—There is the Miracle on your parts; ſee now what God hath done for His Annointed? Call back your memory to the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> look upon Him driven furiouſly from <hi>White-hall,</hi> with His Wife and Children, for feare of His Life, whileſt His own Servants for their ſecurity durſt not be neere him; looke upon him at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> ſcornfully accuſed of leavying Warre againſt Himſelfe, and the Sheriffes and Conſtables appointed to diſperſe his Army; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Him at <hi>Windſor</hi> without ordinary, neceſſary ſupport; think of the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> when you would not vouchſafe to tell Him what you would have, requiring nothing but His ſubmiſſion to your Counſells<hi>:</hi> Remember Him at <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Beverley,</hi> after you had Poſſeſſed your ſelves of all His Armes, Caſtles, Forts, Townes, and Ships, and ſeized upon all the Armes of the Kingdome, ſtopped His Rents, and incenſed the people in all parts againſt Him; Oh thinke upon Him at <hi>Nottingham</hi> when you would not vouchſafe to Treat with Him, only giving your great Generall power of receiving him to mercy, when you had reduced him to that Condition, that He had neither Armes, Men, or Money, or knew as you thought where to have any, and this at a time when you had a wanton flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Army of 10000 men within two dayes March of him, to bring Him back to <hi>London,</hi> here is an Argument for a Miracle; obſerve Him in a moment, as if Regiments fell from the Cloudes, haſting his owne March to the place where he was expected without ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be called upon at <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> view Him at <hi>Edgehill,</hi> with a handfull of men (and if they were more, imagine how he got them) finding out this formidable Army, and diſperſing them, Himſelfe taking as much paines to ſave thoſe who came to deſtroy him, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had done to ſeduce them; Inſtead of being brought up by the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> as by the vote of both Houſes He ought to have been, See Him making his owne way, ſcattering thoſe at <hi>Reading,</hi> and ſhewing himſelfe at <hi>Brainceford,</hi> that if indeed He were ſo much deſired at <hi>London,</hi> and might be worthily received there, they might have their wiſh. Beleeve it Sir, His Majeſty hath not ſo great a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155896:8"/>
Iourney to the Conqueſt of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as he had from <hi>Nottingham</hi> to <hi>Brainceford.</hi> If you cannot ſuddenly find how this Army was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, enquire how it hath been kept together, a fit of Loyalty and Affection, a little diſlike and indignation to ſee a good King ill uſed, might procure a preſent ſupply; but that this Army raiſed without Money, and armed without Weapons, ſhould live and grow ſixe moneths together, that no Souldier ſhould ſtarve for want of Meat, or murmur for want of Pay, that the King ſhould have a Magazine, and you want Armes, that the King ſhould pay his Souldiers, and you have no money, is ſuch an inſtance of the power and preſence of the Almighty, that if any ſuch Argument were currant with you, your principall Members would no longer have tempted God in this Kingdome, but have ſought him in a ſtrange Land. Improve all theſe inſtances by your owne Obſervations, and tell me ſadly on whoſe ſide the Miracles have appeared.</p>
            <p>You would know my Opinion what the Burgeſſe of <hi>D.</hi> ſhould do, and you tell me, his Honour will not ſuffer him too apparantly to recede from thoſe with whom he hath kept ſo much Company. I know not what Counſell to give upon that principle, If his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and his Innocence have not a care of each other, neither can be ſafe; Me thinks the King himſelfe hath given you a rare Pattern of Modeſty in this poynt, he did not ſatisfie himſelfe with conſenting to new lawes, but acknowledged paſſed Errors. Reparation is as Soveraign a thing as Bounty, and except there be this Ingenuity, Reformation can never be perfect, you ſay, he doubts what he hath done formerly will be more remembred then what he hath ſince done or ſhall do for the future; he is too blame, he hath not a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous nor a Chriſtian minde, who thinks ill ſervices may not be throughly repayred by future duty. I am ſo farre from that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as though his miſtakes have been of as ill conſequence to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique as moſt mens, <hi>I</hi> beleive he hath ſo good an opportunity by ſome eminent ſervice to repaire himſelfe, that he may even lay an obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gratitude upon the King, not only to forgive but reward his Affection. There is no ſuch way to have what he now does, not valued, as by juſtifying what he hath done, ſo contrary to this: 'tis no ſcandall to be deceived, leſſe to confeſſe he was ſo. Let him take the ſame paines to oppoſe and ſuppreſſe unreaſonable Perſons, as he doth to perſwade others to conſent to what himſelfe thinks unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155896:9"/>
and the worke is done. As he hath a taske to do ſomewhat that is noble, ſo he hath a faire game before him having done it.</p>
            <p>I know nothing of yours unanſwered, you muſt give me leave hereafter not to beleive you, if you ſtumble any more at theſe ſtraws, rather conſider what he is to Anſwer to God, the King, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Poſterity, that ſits idle without reſiſting the violence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity offered to all foure, that is content to ſee this pretious game of Religion, Liberty and Honour played at other mens Charges, and poſſibly in hazard of being loſt for want of his Aſſiſtance; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether you and the reſt who firſt exerciſed the <hi>Militia</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire,</hi> and ſo diſcompoſed the Government, and firſt taught the People a new obedience, have not to Anſwer for all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and preſſures which have ſince befallen that poor Country. Let thoſe who have contributed to the raiſing, and maintenance of that Rebellious Army, think ſadly, whether they are not guilty of all the blood-ſhed on either ſide, and in this meditation that virtuous Lord, (who had long ſince been ſtarved but for the Kings Meat, and been naked, but for His Clothes,) may find himſelfe guilty of the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Father; Remember the bleſſed Condition we were in Eighteen Moneths ſince, and be proud if you can of the State you have now brought us to. Think of the firm, ſtable happineſſe our Anceſtors enjoyed, and reſolve there cannot be ſecurity but by the ſame Rule. 'Tis not laying down Armes makes a Peace, but ſuch a Vnion of affections, that neither party unpleaſantly remembers the way to it. If King or People be enforced to give away that which properly belongs to them, it will produce rather reſt then Peace, &amp; the memory there of will be ſo greivous to the looſer, that perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Iealouſies, and diſcontents will be between them; Inſiſt upon your Rights, let all doubts which may concern Religion, Liberty, and Property be cleared, &amp; ſecured; Let Parliaments recover their good old Priviledges, theſe are all our Birthrights, and hath been that which hath made the happineſſe and freedom of the Engliſh Nation loved and envyed throughout Chriſtendom; we will not part with a tittle of them, but when they ſhall be in danger will joyn with you in their Defence. But let us reſt here, Preſſe not the King to part with what properly belongs to Him, 'tis our right to ſee that He enjoyes His, the hower that he growes leſſe a King, We have loſt a part of our freedom, if the power of Subjects be once enlarged,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155896:9"/>
we are looſers by it, and affect an Authority will deſtroy us; Do not think the Kings love of Peace, can invite Him to part with the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Peace; what would the world thing of Him, if after the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up Armes for the defence of His own, he ſhould, upon Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he might lay them down again, part with that, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of which He tooke them up? would he not juſtifie what hath been done againſt Him, if He yeelded that now, which if He had 8. Moneths ſince, all this Confuſion they will ſay might have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and will he not leave an excellent Encouragement to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to tread in their Fathers ſteps, and to follow the example of their proſperous wickedneſſe? Do not think a Iewell plucked out of the Royall Diadem, can help it's brightneſſe, and luſtre in any other place, 'tis a loſſe to the Nation, which cannot be repaired by an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of power to private hands; If this be Reaſon, Let not the folly and madneſſe of other people make you quit it; Warre it ſelfe is not halfe ſo greivous, as the Iurisdiction of theſe men who would have you reſigne your underſtanding to their fury and madneſſe. Let them ſhift for themſelves, and you ſhall quickly ſee what a contemptible People they will prove<hi>:</hi> Let Religion, Reaſon, Law, Iuſtice, and Honour be your guides, the Kingdom will flouriſh, and we ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine be happy in each other.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Quarter</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>of</hi> April. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
